gift that's right
gift yeah gift is
gift is one of the
highest things we can do right i mean i
i
i qualify that by saying the gift with
no expectation of return
you take a part of your being
and you separate it from yourself and
you
transfer it to another person
and sometimes a gift has conditions
and sometimes it does not
sometimes a gift has conditions if a
gift has conditions then
it's part of a transaction is it
not it's no longer a gift
so yes it seems like no expectation of
return
is is an essential component of gifting
differentiation between gift and
transaction
by the lack of expectation
of reciprocity so giving a gift is
as if it were the last thing that you
would do
that's nice giving a gift as though it
were the last thing you would do that is
that is the ultimate expression of no
expectation of return i'm just about to
die here you go
well but then but then well i don't need
it anymore right i'm going to die
therefore i can give it away and it's
not it's not
you know there's no cost to me and i
guess
it's not that you give the gift
knowing that you're going to die is you
you give knowing that you might
die in the next set second
and that's what makes the
beauty the transients
i mean that could be applied to every
action that you take
in your life right that should be taken
as though you could die in the next
moment and
is this action worthy of your last act
on this earth
right that's that's a bad way to live
so every action that we take is
a gift if we put it in the right context
which is that this is potentially the
last
thing that we do and so we cannot expect
nothing in return it would be foolhardy
to do so
that's right i could be dead there but
i'm not therefore this moment
is a gift that's a really beautiful way
to look at every moment in your life
i could have died yesterday or five
minutes ago whatever but i didn't
i'm still here
the gift of life which isn't always
a gift or is it a life of great
suffering
is that a gift or is that a burden
and that's one of the great existential
questions isn't it is is is lo
is being worth it even in the face of
great suffering but
i mean there's a very good argument to
be made that suffering is an inevitable
consequence of life and so
bearing that suffering and living on
life as though it were a gift
anyway is suffering itself
a gift is death a gift
is genocide a gift or all these things
gifts
if we can learn from them are they
a gift from the future to the present
and given the inseparability of life
from death then life is no more than a
gift than death is right they are they
are
equally valuable um in in in that sense
um just going back to the notion of the
gift as
a form of sacrifice right the the
giving of a a valuable piece of yourself
a piece of flesh a pound of flesh for a
pound of flesh
one pint of blood for a pint of blood
that's a transactional nature
but then the gift is here is my hand
do what you will with it
there's a boundary to these to the gift
and the transaction
something like giving blood you give
blood
not so that you have it for yourself
later you give blood into a pool but at
the same time you have a reasonable
expectation that should you require
blood
at some point you you know you've
contributed to that pool and thus you
get access to that pool so there's
gifting to the commons the commons is a
place that you can gift to
maybe you will be gifted back but maybe
not it does not matter if you are lucky
you will not need the gift
of somebody else you will be blessed by
the that you do not need a gift
but if you need a gift
yeah gifting to the commons you don't
need to give anything to anyone if
all that is produced all that is created
is immediately gifted to the commons and
becomes accessible to
all yes
the gifting economy that's it done
but no one may lack for anything
and that they may be surprised
with an unexpected gift not something
that they needed but
some joy that they can receive a present
yeah where gifting becomes the normal
right and your status is determined not
by
how much you acquire but how much you
give the the size of your contribution
to the commons is that which determines
your celebrity
if you like in the society right that is
what is honored
competition of giving
a competition of philanthropy you can be
the most
philanthropic who can
give the most joy you can give the most
wealth peace
[Applause]